[music]
>> 2026 release wave one business central
launch edition. This session is what's
new in enhanced Power BI and Excel with
Business Central. My name is Kenny
Pontoppidan. I am very happy to have a
guest speaker with me, Joshua. Do you
want to introduce yourself?
>> Uh so, I'm Joshua.
Um yeah, I work here with Kenny and I'm
excited to show you
what we have built and worked on for
this release and to hear what you think.
So.
Cool.
So,
the investments in this area for this
wave is about three things.
Better or easier ways to demo Power BI
embedded in Business Central.
Also, maximizing the use both for the
Power BI together with Excel but also
Excel uh in general for users. And for
the Power BI apps, we have updated
things related to sales, uh subscription
billing, and inventory.
So, the highlights are as follows. We
are going to start with five clicks to
demo, then moving on to using Excel as a
client for Power BI, using agentic Excel
together with Business Central, some um
some better guidance on how to set up
calendars for your Power BI apps, and
then just uh showcasing or telling you
about the new Power BI apps. Those have
all uh breakout sessions.
So, five clicks to Power BI demo.
We want it to be so easy for partners if
you want to go uh to a prospective
customer and demo the embedded Power BI
reports.
Um this only for now works for demo
companies. Later, we hope to it make
this same setup experience easy in
production environments.
But instead of me talking about slides
and what have you, why don't we have
uh Joshua to show how cool this is. So,
Joshua, over to you.
Okay. So, here we have a evaluation
company
that hasn't configured any of the Power
BI reports that we offer.
So, now the experience will be to go to
the Power BI deployments page
where you can see all of the reports
that we ship out of the box
uh in Business Central.
And here we can select as many as we
want or the ones that we are interested
in.
We can deploy them and this will kick in
the process of
uh going to Power BI, update, and update
with the right version
uh that of the report that corresponds
to your version of of Business Central.
So, yeah.
You can refresh and here we are
following the process of how each is
yeah.
getting installed.
So,
you can also have an overview of the
steps that have been completed along the
way.
And if you don't want to directly
install it and want to see what you want
what you will get,
you can download the PBIX and you can
inspect it for yourself.
Okay. So, now all of them have finished.
And if we go back to our role center
and
see any of our reports for finance,
example, the financial overview,
then it will be opening with the report
that was just uploaded, configured
against your company.
So, hopefully that will make it much
more easy to demo and
once we get to it, also to deploy and
maintain
uh the Power BI uh
apps on your
uh
customer's environments.
So, Joshua, you say, as I understand it,
so by doing this, I can deploy my Power
BI apps to my personal workspace in
Power BI.
And does it also set up refresh? Is Is
that part of it?
>> is not currently part of it, uh but that
is something we are
uh that you would have to configure in
your workspace. So, we can
show that.
>> Also, when you say it has been set up in
uh it means we haven't we have pushed to
Power BI and we have configured inside
Business Central where this is residing.
Yes, we have configured the parameters
and the first refresh has been
scheduled, but if you want to have it
recurringly scheduled, you will have to
do it at least for this release in
uh So,
for example, I can show it here
uh in my workspace. These are the ones
that just got uploaded.
So, you can either refresh now or
schedule a refresh as you would do
before.
>> Very nice.
Thanks a lot, Joshua. I I really hope
that these five clicks
will make the the demos of embedded
Power BI just part of any um any
pre-sales demo with for Business
Central.
Okay, let's shift gears to uh using
Excel together with Power BI.
And um
for many years, actually more than 20
years, with the introduction of analysis
services for SQL Server, analysis
services um had Excel as the main client
to do pivot tables and analyze your OLAP
cubes.
And analysis services later on became
Power BI. So, we thought it would be
valuable to showcase here and in the
documentation how you can use Excel to
do pivoting on your Power BI semantic
models.
The first thing you need to do in Excel
is to set up a connection to your uh
Power BI semantic models. You do that in
get data from fabric and then connect to
your Power BI apps or your Power BI
semantic model.
From there, you then
go to
insert and insert a pivot table, and
then uh from there you can pick the
semantic model as the data source for
the pivot table.
And in this example here, we have an
inventory report based on the inventory
app model. And
then you can slice and dice that
inventory data
the way you want to create your own
reports instead of or maybe as
supplement to the Power BI apps where
it's a visual representation. This is
probably more like a data slice and dice
analysis, but the the model is the same,
the data is the same. It's just using
Excel as the client.
And speaking of Excel, there's another
application that's quite new in the
world of Excel uh called agentic Excel
capabilities. And this works very well
together with edit and or open in Excel
um scenarios, even probably even uh
analyzing financial report uh Excel
outputs or any of the reports that have
an Excel layout as the output. Um we put
some different scenarios described in
our documentation. There's going to
There's a link here in the video for it.
You can also see the navigation there.
And
with with these scenarios, these are
just examples, you can have an agent
inside Excel that reason over your data.
If you use open open in Excel or
financial reporting Excel or
uh a report with an Excel layout, it's
all kind of um
analyzing the data that's there. With
edit in Excel, you can have
agentic Excel be a powerful way to
update data and then you can push that
back to Business Central. So, these are
just more AI capabilities together with
Business Central that
agentic Excel opens up for.
Another enhancement we did to Microsoft
Learn is to to help you configure the
types of calendars you want to use for
your Power BI apps.
Um
our apps actually come with quite
advanced time intelligence. So, there
are many different ways you can
configure your calendars and we probably
hit that a bit a little bit in the setup
pages. So, now it's all in the Business
Central documentation how to set up
different fiscal calendars or week-based
calendars, and that will be reflected in
your Power BI apps, so you can report
on the way your calendar works.
And then
uh we have as I mentioned in the
beginning, we have updated the Power BI
apps specifically for subscription
billing, sales, and inventory. Uh the
the little teacher icon to the top right
means that there there are breakout
sessions uh actually for all three
areas. You can see the links in the
description and probably we'll have
links in the end of this video to to go
learn more.
Um
Yeah, so the the customer retention is a
way to look at customer loyalty.
Uh we also added for inventory ABC
analysis, so you can do those type of
uh item sales analysis um to to find out
like highly valuable
uh items that you must have on
inventory.
And then for subscription billing, we
did a full overview
uh not overview, a full makeover of the
visuals so that they align together with
the other all the other apps.
So, if you want to learn more about the
things we discussed today, uh your
friend in Microsoft Learn is aka.ms/bc
analytics.
That takes you to the overview page of
anything related to this topic and you
find the new pages on the date calendar
um things around
a gigantic Excel in the Excel section
and of course the updates will be to the
different Power BI apps will be in their
own sections under inventory,
subscription, billing, and sales.
If you like the content here, you
probably also like other analytic
sessions. So, there are many different
related sessions to to to this both in
the space of analytical content, so
sales, inventory, finance, finance
financial reporting, subscription
billing, but also maybe related enhanced
analysis mode and and demo data. So, any
of these topics might be of interest.
Check out the links below
to to learn or to get more into these
breakout sessions.
And with that, I think we are done.
Joshua and I, I want to thank Joshua for
coming in and show you the great demo.
And we hope that you will have a great
Business Central launch edition.
Yeah. Thank you.
We have compiled a number of general
resources that we believe are key both
for partners, but also Business Central
customers. Most Some of these are
partner, some of them are also for
customers. So, the first one is
called aka.ms/bcall.
This is a partner resource for that
contains lists of every other aka link
that is needed for you to understand
anything about both the Business Central
product, but also processes around it.
We call these aka links because they are
called aka.ms and then for for
something. And with Business Central
links, we all always prefix with BC and
then something.
The next one is our partner network
social media for for Business Central
partners Viva Viva Engage. So,
aka.ms/bcvivaengage
is where you go and interact with other
partners. It's not open for customers.
So, this is where you can ask the
questions, interact with the product
group, interact with with with each
other
in a in a closed network.
Second link a third link is for both
partners and customers. We are called
office hours. So, office hours is
something we do once or twice a month
from the product group engaging with the
community about new features or things
we want to discuss. aka.ms/bcofficehours
is the is the place where you go to find
out about upcoming events.
These are recorded. I believe the
recordings are available only to
partners, but the live events are
available to customers as well.
Fourth link is YouTube our YouTube
channel. I'll talk about that
in the next slide and LinkedIn in the
next slide.
And then finally for for Microsoft
partners, the BCs aka.ms/bcpartnerportal
is where you get
a lot of the resources as a partner such
as compete decks,
pitch decks, and a lot of other
resources.
For LinkedIn, this is our product
group's LinkedIn profile. We have 30k or
more followers. So, both partners and
customers. This is the place where we
from the product group put in news and
small bits of information outside the
quote unquote official channel. So,
follow us on LinkedIn to learn what's
happening right now
in in this in the around the product.
And then
also on our YouTube channel where this
is where you're probably watching this
aka.ms/bcyoutube.
We put in not only these launch editions
twice a year, but also
co-pilot and AI videos, shorts, tips and
tricks, technical deep dives, under the
hood.
We even have this what's cooking where
we put little nuggets of of videos out
for new features that are even coming in
on the YouTube channel before
they're coming in the release notes. So,
watch
and maybe bookmark us on YouTube and
also notice all the playlists. So, that
all the content is also organized in
areas, not only all the videos. So, if
you have an area that's has special
interest such as analytics,
you can find an
a playlist and kind of see all the
content related to that.
And that's it. That is truly it. We
won't
There will be no more. So, thank you for
watching all the way to the end.
And again, have a great day. Thank you.